<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes" ?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Emotion Dynamics on Will Hipson</title>
    <link>/tags/emotion-dynamics/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Emotion Dynamics on Will Hipson</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <copyright>&amp;copy; 2019</copyright>
    <lastBuildDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate>
    
	<atom:link href="/tags/emotion-dynamics/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    
    
    <item>
      <title>The Face of (Dis)Agreement - Intraclass Correlations</title>
      <link>/post/emotion-expression-icc/emotion-expression/</link>
      <pubDate>Mon, 04 Feb 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/emotion-expression-icc/emotion-expression/</guid>
      <description>I was recently introduced to Google Dataset Search, an extension that searches for open access datasets. There I stumbled upon this dataset on childrens’ and adult’s ratings of facial expressions. The data comes from a published article by Vesker et al. (2018). Briefly, this study involved having adults and 9-year-old children rate a series of 48 faces on two dimensions of emotion, valence (positive vs. negative) and arousal (activated vs.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Plotting the Affect Circumplex in R</title>
      <link>/post/circumplex/circumplex/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 15 Jan 2019 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/post/circumplex/circumplex/</guid>
      <description>I’m a strong adherent to the circumplex model of emotions introduced by James Russell in the late 1980s. Russell argued that all emotional experience can be boiled down to two dimensions: valence and arousal, with valence being how positive or negative you feel and arousal being how sluggish or emotionally activated you feel. The emotions we commonly label as anger, sadness, joy, etc. can be mapped within this affective two-dimensional space, such that joy is a high valence, high arousal emotion, whereas boredom is a moderately low valence and low arousal emotion.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emotion Dynamics of Solitude</title>
      <link>/project/emotion-dynamics/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/emotion-dynamics/</guid>
      <description>We often think of emotions as being there one moment and gone the next. However, we are always experiencing some sort of emotion - whether it&amp;rsquo;s boiling anger or vapid listlessness. The study of emotion dynamics is all about how emotions change over time. Emotions can change from one moment to the next - intensifying or deintensifying. I&amp;rsquo;m interested in exploring what predicts these complex changes. In particular, I&amp;rsquo;m interested in whether solitude impacts our emotional state.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Emotion Regulation</title>
      <link>/project/emotion-regulation/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 09 Jan 2019 00:00:00 -0500</pubDate>
      
      <guid>/project/emotion-regulation/</guid>
      <description></description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>